So, I kind of believe that we're in like the "cave-painting" era of computer interfaces.
أذن, أعتقد بأننا الآن في عهد الرسم في الكهوف فيما يخص واجهات الحاسب
Like, they're very kind of -- they don't go as deep or as emotionally engaging as they possibly could be
مثل، أنها لا تتعمق، أو تعطي الإحساس بالتفاعل، كما يمكنها أن تكون
and I'd like to change all that.
أريد تغيير كل هذا
Hit me.
لنبدأ
OK. So I mean, this is the kind of status quo interface, right?
حسناً. أعني، هذا هو النوع التقليدي للواجهات، صحيح؟
It's very flat, kind of rigid.
أنها مسطّحة، نوعاً ما جامدة
And OK, so you could sex it up and like go to a much more lickable Mac,
و، حسناً، يمكنك تحسينها وجعلها جاذبة مثل طعامة الماك
you know, but really it's the kind of same old crap we've had for the last,
حقيقة، أنها أنواع مملة من الواجهات القديمة التي عرفناها
you know, 30 years.
تعرفون، خلال الثلاثين سنة الماضية
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
Like I think we really put up with a lot of crap with our computers.
أعني، أعتقد أننا عالقين مع الكثير من الملل في حاسباتنا
I mean it's point and click, it's like the menus, icons, it's all the kind of same thing.
أعني، مثل المؤشر، والنقر، مثل القوائم، الإيقونات، إنها نفس الشئ
And so one kind of information space that I take inspiration from is my real desk.
وأحد فضاءات المعلومات التي تلهمني هي مكتبي الحقيقي
It's so much more subtle, so much more visceral
أنه ممتلئ للغاية، ومحشو بشدة
-- you know, what's visible, what's not.
تعرفون، ما هو ظاهر، أو غير ظاهر
And I'd like to bring that experience to the desktop.
وأردت نقل هذه التجربة الى سطح مكتب الحاسب
So I kind of have a -- this is BumpTop.
لذا فقد وصلت لهذه الواجهة للمستخدم "بمب توب"
It's kind of like a new approach to desktop computing.
أنها مقاربة جديدة نوعا ما لسطح مكتب الحاسب
So you can bump things -- they're all physically, you know, manipulable and stuff.
أذن يمكنك صدم الأشياء -- كأنها مادية، تعرفون، ترتيبها وما إلى ذلك
And instead of that point and click, it's like a push and pull,
وبدلاً عن المؤشر والنقر، أنها تدفع وتسحب
things collide as you'd expect them. Just like on my real desk,
الملفات تتصادم كما تتوقعها. مثل سطح المكتب الحقيقي
I can -- let me just grab these guys -- I can turn things into piles
أستطيع -- مهلاً حتى أرتب أمسك بهذا -- يمكنني تحويل الأشياء الى أكوام
instead of just the folders that we have.
بدلاً عن المجلدات التي لدينا
And once things are in a pile I can browse them by throwing them into a grid,
وبمجرد أن تكون الأشياء في أكوام، أستطيع إستكشافها عبر رميها في شبكة
or you know, flip through them like a book
أو، تعرفون، تصفحها مثل الكتاب
or I can lay them out like a deck of cards.
أو فرشها مثل أوراق اللعب
When they're laid out, I can pull things to new locations or delete things
عندما تكون مفروشة، أستطيع سحب الملفات لموقع آخر، أو أحذف الملفات
or just quickly sort a whole pile, you know, just immediately, right?
أو ترتيب الأكوام بسرعة، تعرفون، في الحال، صحيح
And then, it's all smoothly animated, instead of these jarring changes you see in today's interfaces.
وبعد ذلك، تتحرك بسلاسة، بدلاً عن التغييرات المتضاربة التي نراها في واجهات الحاسبات اليوم
Also, if I want to add something to a pile, well, how do I do that?
أيضاً، اذا أردت إضافة شيئ الى الكومة، حسناً، كيف يمكنني فعل ذلك؟
I just toss it to the pile, and it's added right to the top. It's a kind of nice way.
فقط أرميها الى الكومة، وسيتم إضافتها الى قمة الكومة. أنها طريقة لطيفة
Also some of the stuff we can do is,
أيضاً، بعض الأمور التي يمكننا فعلها
for these individual icons we thought -- I mean,
بالنسبة لتلك الإيقونات المنفردة فكرنا -- أعني
how can we play with the idea of an icon, and push that further?
كيف يمكننا التلاعب على فكرة الإيقونات، وندفع بها قدماً؟
And one of the things I can do is make it bigger
وبعض الحركات الممكنة أن أجلعها أكبر
if I want to emphasize it and make it more important.
اذا ما أردت التأكيد على أنها أكثر أهمية
But what's really cool is that since there's a physics simulation running under this,
لكن الشئ الأكثر لطفاً أن هناك محاكاة فيزيائية تعمل في الخلفية
it's actually heavier. So the lighter stuff doesn't really move
في الحقيقة هي أثقل. لذا فالملفات الأخف لا يمكنها إزاحتها
but if I throw it at the lighter guys, right?
لكن اذا رميتها على الملفات الأخف، صحيح؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So it's cute, but it's also like a subtle channel of conveying information, right?
لذا فهي لطيفة، وهي أيضاً مثل قناة بارعة لإرسال المعلومات، صحيح؟
This is heavy so it feels more important. So it's kind of cool.
هذا ثقيل، أذن يبدو أكثر أهمية. أذن فهو نوع ما لطيف
Despite computers everywhere paper really hasn't disappeared,
رغماً عن الحاسبات في كل مكان، لم تختفي الأوراق
because it has a lot of, I think, valuable properties.
لأنها تمتلك الكثير من، أعتقد، الصفات القيّمة
And some of those we wanted to transfer to the icons in our system.
وبعضها نريد أن ننقلها الى الإيقونات في نظامنا
So one of the things you can do to our icons, just like paper, is crease them and fold them,
وأحد أشياء التي يمكن فعلها للإيقونات، مثل الورق، ثنيها، وطويها
just like paper. Remember, you know, something for later.
تماماً مثل الأوراق. تذكر، أنه شئ لما بعد
Or if you want to be destructive, you can just crumple it up
أو، اذا أردت أن تكون مدمرا، يمكنك كرمشتها
and, you know, toss it to the corner.
وتعرفون، رميها الى الزاوية
Also just like paper, around our workspace
وأيضاً مثل الورق، في مكان العمل
we'll pin things up to the wall to remember them later,
يمكن تعليق الملفات على الحائط لنتذكرها لاحقاً
and I can do the same thing here,
ويمكنني فعل نفس الشئ هنا
and you know, you'll see post-it notes and things like that around people's offices.
وتعرفون، سترى مذكرات وأمورا من هذا القبيل حول المكاتب
And I can pull them off when I want to work with them.
وأستطيع سحبها عندما أريد أن أعمل بها
So, one of the criticisms of this kind of approach to organization is that,
أذن، أحد الإنتقادات لهذه الطريقة في التنظيم هي
you know, "Okay, well my real desk is really messy. I don't want that mess on my computer."
تعرفون، "حسناً، مكتبي الحقيقي فوضوي. لا أريد هذه الفوضى في حاسبي"ـ
So one thing we have for that is like a grid align,
أذن، أحد الحلول لهذه المشكلة هي الترتيب كشبكة
kind of -- so you get that more traditional desktop. Things are kind of grid aligned.
نوعا ما -- تحصلون على سطح مكتب أكثر تقليدية. ترتيب الملفات كالشبكة
More boring, but you still have that kind of colliding and bumping.
مملة أكثر، لكن ما يزال بإستطاعتكم صدم الملفات و رجها
And you can still do fun things like make shelves on your desktop.
ويمكنك فعل أشياء مرحة مثل الرفوف على سطح مكتبك
Let's just break this shelf. Okay, that shelf broke.
لنكسر هذا الرف، حسناً، كسر الرف
I think beyond the icons, I think another really cool domain for this software --
أعتقد أبعد من الإيقونات، هناك مجال آخر لطيف لهذا البرنامج -ـ
I think it applies to more than just icons and your desktop -- but browsing photographs.
أعتقد أنه ينطبق على أكثر من مجرد إيقونات وسطح مكتبك -- بل تصفح الصور
I think you can really enrich the way we browse our photographs
أعتقد بإمكانك إثراء الطريقة التي نتصفح بها الصور
and bring it to that kind of shoebox of, you know, photos with your family on the kitchen table kind of thing.
وجعلها مثل الصندوق، تعرفون، الصور مع الأسرة على طاولة المطبخ وهذا النوع من الأمور
I can toss these things around. They're so much more tangible and touchable --
يمكنني إلقاءها. تكون محسوسة أكثر عندما -- وملموسة -ـ
and you know I can double-click on something to take a look at it.
وتعرفون يمكنني النقر عليها مرتين لمشاهدة واحدة منها
And I can do all that kind of same stuff I showed you before.
ويمكن فعل كل الحركات التي عرضتها عليكم سابقاً
So I can pile things up, I can flip through it, I can, you know --
أذن يمكنني تكويم الملفات، يمكنني قلبها، يمكنني، تعرفون -ـ
okay, let's move this photo to the back, let's delete this guy here,
حسناً، لنحرك هذه الصورة الى الخلف، ولنحذف هذا الملف هنا
and I think it's just a much more rich kind of way of interacting with your information.
وأعتقد أنها طريقة أكثر ثراءً للتفاعل مع المعلومات
And that's BumpTop. Thanks!
وهذا هو "بمب توب". شكراً